Guide to the Nikki Van Hightower Papers
University of Houston Libraries
- Speeches and Presentations
  - Women in Business and Political Life
    - Nursing, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Personnel Organization, undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - The Politics of Affirmative Action, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - The Power Structure: How to Achieve it and Use it Effectively, undated (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Pressure Group, undated (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Professional Women in Political Life, undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Progress of the Professional Woman in the Working World, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Public Relations, undated (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Role of Women in the Political Process, undated (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Secretaries, undated (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Status of Women in Business, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - What Do Business Women Want?, undated (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - What is Discrimination?, undated (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Women and Employment, undated (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Women at the Top: More Humanity or More of the Same?, undated (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Women Democrats, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Women, Employment Discrimination and Aging, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Women in Politics, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Women in Radio (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Women in Science (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Women in the Military, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Women's Route to Elective Office, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Untitled, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Women in Crisis
    - Battered Women, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Bay Area Turning Point Auxiliary Club Address, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Enforcement of Laws, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Houston Area Women's Center, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Houston Police Department In service on Battering, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Politics of Women in Crisis, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Pornography: the Abuse of Freedom, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Public Price Tag of Violence in the Home, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Rape Program, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Testimony on Sexually Oriented Businesses, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - What Is Sexual Harassment?, undated (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Women and Drugs, undated (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects
    - Art as a Vehicle for Social Change, undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Censorship, undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Freedom and Rights of the Press, the Reporter and the Public, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Naturalization Ceremony Address, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - The Politics of Health Care, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Rising Energy Costs, the Squeeze on the Consumer, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - The Sociology of Diving, undated (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Speech for John Anderson, undated (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Testimony Before the Texas Senate Against Senate Bill #119 Limiting Abortion Benefits to Public Employees, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Testimony Supporting "Americans With Disabilities" Act, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Untitled, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Ephemera for Grenias Campaign, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Untitled - Awards and Toasts, undated (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Speaking Engagement Arrangements
    - Arrangements and Correspondence, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Arrangements and Correspondence, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 2-8)
    - Messages/Notes, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Personal Files
  This series contains thirty-eight folders of material dating from 1974 to 1997, with the bulk of the material from 1974 to 1989. Correspondence files contain a variety of communications relating to Van Hightower's involvement in clubs and committees, notifications of awards and honors, letters of thanks and congratulations, and letters from personal friends and family. Correspondents of note include Betty Ford, Ann Richards, Liz Carpenter, and Eleanor Tinsley. A significant portion of the correspondence could be considered "business" rather than personal. Since it is difficult, however, to determine the division between Van Hightower's personal and official community involvement, most of the correspondence was left in these personal files, with the exception of some material pertaining to the Houston Area Women's Center. Van Hightower's resume, in box 12 folder 13, provides a comprehensive survey of her achievements. The series also contains some photographs which are filed with accompanying correspondence, or at the end of the series.
  - Articles and Papers, 1974-1989 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Assorted Material, 1978-1982 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Assorted Material, 1983-1985 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Assorted Material, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Engagement Diaries, 1980-1981 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Legal Documents, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Messages/Notes, 1983-1986 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Resumes, 1979-1997 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - University of Houston Class, 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - University of Houston Class - Financial Records, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - University of Houston Class - Miscellany, 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Photographs
    - Athanaskos, Elizabeth, undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Hide Inspector Award, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Miller, Rex; Van Hightower, Nikki, undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Van Hightower, Nikki, undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Van Hightower, Nikki - Unidentified Event and People, undated (Box 12, Folder 21-22)
    - Y.M.C.A. Membership Campaign (L to R): Fickessen, A.J; Speer, Sharon; Van Hightower, Nikki; Joiner, Joe, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Y.M.C.A. Membership Campaign (L to R): Guyon, Judge J.D.; Speer, Sharon; Fickessen, A.J.; Van Hightower; Nikki; Joiner, Joe, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Y.M.C.A. Membership Campaign (L to R): Joiner, Joe; Speer, Sharon; Fickessen, A.J.; Van Hightower, Nikki, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Y.M.C.A. Membership Campaign (L to R): Lewes, Stan; Van Hightower, Nikki; Fickessen, A.J., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Y.M.C.A. Membership Campaign (L to R): Van Hightower, Nikki; Unidentified, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Y.M.C.A. Membership Campaign (L to R): Van Hightower, Nikki; Unidentified; Fickessen, A.J., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Y.M.C.A. Membership Campaign: Van Hightower, Nikki, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 29)
- Clippings
  There are twenty-seven folders in this series, containing newspaper clippings and magazine articles dating from 1973 to 1992. The material is arranged into subjects which, where possible, reflect series titles, and is ordered chronologically within folders. The clippings provide extensive coverage of some of the key points in Van Hightower's career. Van Hightower's election campaign for City Council is documented more fully here than in the Political Publicity series. Also prominently represented are the offices of Women's Advocate and County Treasurer. Newspaper clippings have been photocopied for preservation reasons.
  - City Council Election Campaign, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - City Council Election Campaign, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - County Treasurer, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - County Treasurer, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - County Treasurer Commissioners Salary Increase, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - County Treasurer, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Houston Area Women's Center, 1978-1989 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Houston Area Women's Center, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - International Women's Year
    - National Conference, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - National Conference, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - National Conference, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - National Conference, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Texas Women's Meeting, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Involvement in the Women's Movement, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1979 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980-1984 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985-1991 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Speech Material, 1989-1992 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - State Treasurer Campaign, 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Women's Advocate, 1975-1976 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Women's Advocate, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 23-25)
    - Women's Advocate, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - Women's Advocate, undated (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Oversizse clippings and newspapers (Box 14, Item 1)